I heard an interesting rumour about a Banuk camp.
They say the Banuk there live alongside machines, peaceful as you like.
Keep 'em, use 'em, sing to 'em.
If it's true, if we learned how they do it,
think how valuable that would be to all the tribes!
When you say valuable, you mean they'd pay you for it?
Heh, the last bunch just wanted to know about the reward.
You're a smart one.
I hired men to investigate.
Just investigate, that's all.
Those Banuk are canny, too canny.
I paid up front, well, half up front.
I've had no word back.
So now you're hiring someone to find the last men you hired.
If it's true they walk among machines without fear in this camp.
Well, you can't miss that, can you?
I think I'm in the clear.
[whistle]
Never know when I might need these.
I'll do what I have to.
[whistle]
Okay, they're heading back.
Now they're hunting me.
Ho!
Glad I found this.
Let's get this over with.
It'd be fascinating, if they weren't looking for me.
That's it, nothing to see here.
Got it!
Just go about your business.
Good, I can use this.
Dawn breaking, every time's different.
Hope you'll go quietly.
Low and quiet does it.
[whistles]
Ah, perfect!
A little more…
Ready or not!
Red light means trouble!
Getting soaked from melted snow.
This has to be the Banuk camp that Vilgund told me about.
So what happened to the other mercenaries he sent?
The machines are docile.
It's like they've already been overridden.
[Banuk hunter]
I don't like spending so long away from the hunt.
It makes my muscles twitch.
[Aluki]
The last hunt was a good one.
To see these machines up close like this, it's…
Grazer dung.
I'm sorry?
Frozen Grazer dung.
This Ravager led me here.
I chased it down from the Rivals, where it killed a great ice hunter.
Tore him in two.
A challenge I accepted.
But when it reached this camp the fury left it.
Isn't that a good thing?
Tikuk says it's a gift.
Pff, what is a gift but a reward that you didn't earn?
The machines are meant to challenge us!
Now I'm stuck here guarding the Shamans.
[Banuk hunter]
We should find a few machines, earn the spirit's favour.
Greetings Nora, I am Tikuk.
Shaman, I've never seen anything like this.
[laughs]
The blue light is strong here.
My people travelled far from the heights of Ban-Ur
to experience it for themselves.
The "blue light"?
The light of the machine spirits.
It is all around us.
It settles upon us.
This is how it used to be before they grew angry.
I know about the Derangement,
but I didn't think the machines were ever this calm.
What is it about this place?
We don't really know.
We sing and we listen to the machine songs.
The machines sing to you?
To each other.
You are a hunter.
You must have heard their communions and hymns, their calls and cries.
We're not meant to understand, but we Shamans try to interpret.
What is the song that angered them so?
That turned them upon us?
What song soothes them?
I was drawn to this place in a storm.
At first I thought the keening was the wind,
snapping off the mountain's frozen face.
But no, it was the Thunderjaw's song.
I found it crouched on its haunches.
Its metal unmoving, and I took shelter beneath it.
When the storm cleared, its singing done,
perhaps the spirit left its great shell.
Or perhaps it slumbers and remains.
So we have not stripped and gleaned this one.
We treat it with the care it is owed.
Tikuk, have any other outlanders come through here recently?
Some Oseram, yes.
They were convinced the machines were "malfunctioning".
As if machines were mere devices in need of repair.
Well, that is how the Oseram see the world, is it not?
They ate with us, then when they were satisfied
there was nothing they could explain, they left with the northern light.
Do you mind if I look around more Tikuk?
Speak, trade, listen. You are welcome. No harm will come to you here.
So it's not the Banuk that are doing this.
There's something about this place.
They can't see it, but maybe my Focus can.
Shaman, you're trying to understand the machines here too?
Yes, Nora.
And taking my time with my studies.
Between you, me, and the spirits, I appreciate the peace.
Not just from the machines.
There are many changes in Ban-Ur.
The hunters and Shamans bicker without end.
What about?
How best to deal with a harsher world.
The hunters, they don't want it back the way it used to be.
And we Shamans find ourselves able to explain less and less.
So many are exiles now, sent to wander.
Here, no-one argues.
So I welcome mystery.
Can my Focus show me anything?
[Banuk hunter]
Keep your skills sharp.
Well prepared for the hunt.
There, a signal, and the source is at the top of the mountain.
I'd better look into it.
[Banuk]
I'm glad to see you…
This is how the Banuk must have gotten up and down the mountain.
Glinthawks are just waiting.
A good sign, I guess.
Someone's been up here recently.
Is that voices?
[in the distance]
You can't just leave us here!
Did Vilgund send you?
I guess shards can buy a conscience.
Never mind that.
Nora girl, you have to stop the others up ahead.
We snuck up here, uncovered some kind of ancient device.
Plain as an anvil that's what affects the machines.
The other bungheads voted to take it to Pitchcliff for auction.
But it's taken a beating already, like it dropped from the sky.
We tried to stop them digging it out.
Without that thing up here, those Banuk will be massacred.
I'll stop them.
You two get out of here.
Sounds like you've already done enough damage.
Well, that's a fair appraisal.
[in the distance]
What did you let the rope slip for?
You bunch of chuffskulls.
[in the distance]
The slack was on your end.
I think it's okay.
[in the distance]
Looks like it's okay, doesn't it?
It's only split in half.
[in the distance]
Get a whiff of that smoke, it's burned out.
What have you done?
Who are you?
You're not one of those Banuk.
I'm too late.
Let me look at it!
Hold on, hold on.
This was our delve.
We did the work.
You want to put your axe in, what's this thing worth to you?
It's worth more to me than you are.
You still want to negotiate?
I don't know about this.
This was your idea.
You started it, you can finish.
Forget it, all the east's ever given me is black toes.
They've made a mess off this.
"Catastrophic malfunction"?
This is from long ago.
And it's been sending a signal all this time, fading out.
I have to get back to the camp before the machines tear it apart.
No! They've already started attacking.
[Aluki]
The hunt is back!
[Tikuk]
The machines are angered, keep your distance!
Hunters, defend the camp. Do what you must.
[Aluki]
Yes, roar and rend at me! I don't fear it.
Now you'll hear my song, machine! A sharp song!
[Aluki]
The hunt is back!
So much for Tikuk's peace. It was only a side effect.
He's not gonna be happy about this.
[Banuk hunter]
That was a little too easy.
[Aluki]
This long hunt is over.
Nora, did you know this change would come upon us?
Not exactly.
Although I know there is a lot changing in our world.
This time, it was outsiders. Those Oseram thought…
The Oseram do not think!
They will never understand the balance between us.
Between man and machine.
Now the blue light has gone and we are left with many songs,
but more for mourning than gratitude.
So what now?
Will you go back to your homeland?
When we teach the young to walk on shifting ice,
we say the secret is taking one step, then the next.
Perhaps one day we will understand the machines' mysteries.
I hope so. Good luck, Tikuk.
[Banuk]
Oh well.
Ah, this scrapes!
They're scanning for me.
Snow haze, white as bone. Huh, that thought got dark.
Here they come.
They know I'm here now.
[Bandit]
Got picked off.
The machine saw me.
Ha ha, I dropped it!